this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the party
okay so welcome listeners to another
episode on soft engineering radio this
time we have invited duck Simon from Sun
labs to talk about some java virtual
machine implementation project called
maxine welcome doc thank you very much
doc would you introduce yourself to our
listeners so I'm Doug Simon as mentioned
and I work here at Sun Microsystems labs
in California at the Menlo Park campus
and I've been a staff member here since
2001 but I actually was here early in 98
as an intern and worked on a project
called spotless VM which morphed into
something called the KVM and became the
reference implementation for the CL DC
implement eight specification when it
went out I think in 2000 and prior to
that I completed a CS degree at the
University of Queensland in Brisbane
Australia under Christina cifuentes
where I worked or my final thesis on his
thesis was in the era of D compilation
where I was looking at mechanisms for
recovering C like control constructs
from assembly code but since being back
in 2001 my focus has been almost and
solely on JVM and you're now working on
on another JVM called Maxine can you
tell a little bit more what what is
Maxine what is it about okay so the
origins of this project can probably be
traced back to the mid 90s Oh a couple
of researchers at sun labs by the name
of david Unger and Mario Bosco were
interested in researching hardware
support for objects in the context of a
managed runtime in particular in context
of a VM so what they were interested is
looking at object references which
aren't necessarily addresses to
flat piece of memory but indexes into
some hardware based object table and
they felt well to conduct an experiment
let's use an existing VM and modify what
exactly means to reference and
dereference objects and in surveying the
landscape they found such an experiment
may not be so easy to conduct given that
there's you know that this concept of
what an object is and how you
dereference it these traditionally
spread across most parts of a VM
implementation or significant parts and
to conduct the experiment they need to
understand vast quantities of any VM so
they got to thinking about how one could
design a VM where this subsystem of
looking at objects or handling objects
is sort of as contained as possible and
disentangle it from as much of the rest
of the VM as possible
so the sort of realization they had is
one of the core architectural concepts
of maxeen and they sort of decided that
if you can build it build a VM around an
opt-in optimizing compiler where the
knowledge of any subsystem is
bootstrapped into the compiler then you
get this disentanglement for free and
hopefully is inlaid parts of interview
it'll become clear what I mean by this
this bootstrapped optimizing compiler
and so that's that's where the idea set
for awhile
around I'm not sure what data was I
think two thousand three or four BAM
Attica came back to the labs after being
in product land at Sun where he was the
tech lead on what's called the CLD c-h-i
the COTC hotspot implementation vm so
that's in the same space as the k vm but
a more optimized implementation of these
small VMS
and he was interested in subscapular
nerve and previous projects and scaling
them up into a new type of full j2se vm
and he shared a lot of the ideas Mario
and Dave had and thus began the Maxine
project and that was around 2005 I
joined in 2006 and we've had subsequent
team members joined since then Lauren
Dan des Michael Van Deventer and pent
Itza we also had someone else working as
an early contributor Greg right so the
VM itself is written in Java we've we
used the latest Java language syntax as
of Java 1.5 in particular we've made
heavy use of annotations to sort of
basically to write a VM which other VM
in Java you have to depending on your
point of view extend or break the
language but you know to write a garbage
collector we need to be able to talk
about such things as pointers which
obviously you can't natively do in Java
so through sort of a combination of
annotations and other mechanisms we've
added basically we have a new type
hierarchy a separate type Ariake in the
language which allows us to do these
low-level operations and then the trick
is to build on top of this this what
we're after is a highly modular
component eyes design so that we can do
these experiments on VM subsystems
without having to necessarily him to
understand every other part of the VM
and not only ask but would like to know
prototype have other researchers in the
vm community be able to use this
artifact to conduct their research I
guess yeah that the core ideas build
everything around an opt-in rise in
compartment if you'd like I'll go into
more detail on what that means
implementing a java virtual machine in
java sounds a bit crazy from the first
point of view that the end that is a
very justified correct initial reaction
which you know i I had as well and the
the this actually has a history in sun
labs we had a project here in 98 called
Java in Java which was exactly that a
Java VM written in Java running on top
of another job of VM and not
surprisingly I think we found that
performed on the order of a thousand
times slower than a standard Java VM so
you're right in that the naive approach
definitely doesn't buy you anything
actually cost you a lot but if you think
about what a VM for any language does or
on a VM at least that has a platform
independent by code format to machine
code compiler in it does at runtime it
runs this compiler over a set of class
files producing machine code which is
directly executing the hardware so if
you can sort of push that understanding
one step further and say well what if we
actually not just put that machine code
into the runtime memory and executed
that but saved it to a file and so in
some sense you can deploy or execute
your compiler in this manner and what we
call ahead of time compilation running
your compiler written in Java as a java
application on top of an existing vm but
saving the the compiled machine code and
the associated objects to a file what
you effectively have is an executable
produced by your compiler that contains
your compiler and the rest of the run
time system necessary to have a
standalone bootstrapped vm doesn't mean
that you first run your your own vm that
is written in java on top of another
java vm let the JIT compiler compile
your your your java vm itself somehow
and then save that's the the produced
the produced machine code to a file and
start from there again without a host vm
exactly
exactly so we have I mean if you think
about C compilers C compilers now what
are they written in they're written in C
so you do need a pre-existing C compiler
to to actually bootstrap a C compiler in
some sense this is no different at some
point as with you know most C compilers
would like to bootstrap LVM with Alvia
but for now until we get the performance
we need it's it's expedient to use an
existing VM you know hotspot being the
obvious and natural candidate so it's in
some sense not too different from you
know the way you bootstrap any other
compiler based system
it's just that typically this is not how
Java VMs have been built why did you
choose Java as a language uh so we
wanted to build a Java VM now why did we
choose you know Java is the
implementation language as well as the
target language well this is not the
first VM to to take this approach and
and realize some of the benefits of
doing this in the Java space we have the
jikes
our VM employs a similar technique as
does the squeak VM this more top VM
written in a subset of Smalltalk
in addition we have another project here
which I was part of called squawk which
is a cotc class VM itself also written
in Java but by implementing in Java
itself you get a lot of the nice
features of the Java language which one
could argue you know make it a more
productive implementation choice than
something like C or C++ for example in
our class loader the vm class letter we
can write this in Java using exceptions
when things go wrong we don't have to
pass all sorts of macros around to to
recover in a safe manner actually and
even more importantly we get garbage
collection for free there's large parts
of a VM that use dynamic memory that
you know part of the GC implementation
itself and if you ever look at the hot
spot source code every time a Java
object finds itself down in the C++
source code they have to have a separate
mechanism to let the garbage collector
know about the C code holding on to or
having a reference to these objects it's
something they call handles which adds a
level of inefficiency in handling these
objects and also it can be a nasty
source of a source of nasty bugs if you
forget to use handles in the right place
we don't have to worry about forgetting
because the language we are compiling
and writing the VM itself is garbage
collected there's other benefits such as
diminishing does the the barrier between
the application code and the VM every
time the application makes a call into
some VM subsystem if you cross this
language barrier from Java to see you
need to perform extra work your layout
of frames may be different depending how
you write your Java compiler that may
well differ to the frame layout used by
the C compiler and so you need to
shuffle things around you need to
effectively marshal things into
potential into different locations
every time you cross that barrier not to
mention having to wrap objects in
handles so there's that sort of overhead
of going through the barrier execution
over it but there's also a barrier to
optimization we can actually inline
parts of the VM into application code
and you know obtain all the well-known
benefits of inlining and this this has
actually been taken one step further by
another project here which is built on
and using the maxine vm chord guest VM
run by Mick Jordan where he is putting
Maxine directly on top of Zen
where yes he's now at the point of
rewriting the thread scheduler so he can
effectively optimize make optimization
decisions that are in a boil down
unaware of the thread scheduling logic
straight from the application code you
can also optimize all the way down
through the network stack so you get
this sort of this diminishing barrier to
both execution overhead and optimize
ability so these are just some of the
benefits of doing it in Java and then
there's this great tool support for Java
that works pretty much the same on all
platforms even though our primary target
or initial target for this VM is a AMD
64 system the members of the team can
quite happily develop compile and debug
most of the VM using a standard Java IDE
on you know our platforms of choice
currently we all develop at various
times on a Macbook on the Solaris system
on a Linux system etc and then we also
get ya the portability aspect is it's
just in general the portability java
brings to applications we get a large
part of for the VM other parts such as
adaptive optimization can be applied to
the VM itself around times at the VM can
sort of trace trace its own execution
and start rearranging or inline in its
code differently so all those
optimizations so that we know that yes
yes I mean this did the ultimate goal is
to apply all well-known vm optimizations
to not just the application code hotspot
cannot dynamically optimize itself once
the VM is being deployed they didn't
write and they don't control the C+ C++
compiler and and it's it's sort of fixed
in stone once once the
thing is out there and running that been
said you know to realize this this an
ultimate goal of optimizing all over the
place
we actually need to implement those
optimizations and given that the
optimizations determine the quality of
the VM you know we have the sort of dog
food principle here once once your dog
foods of a reasonable quality can only
get better and exponentially so until
you're at that point you you actually
have something that can be quite
substandard compared to an existing vm
built around a compiler that's you know
thirty or forty years old and quite
mature so that's that sort of the
trade-off one one buys into with this
approach so maxine is called a matter
circular vm what does this medicine
plate effect so it's it's I think it's
it's hard to nail down this definition
and and so we've chosen a you know put a
stake in the in the ground and said in
the context of this project we basically
mean a vm that's implemented in the
language it it hosts and and tries to
express as much of the vm semantics in
that language
without having to hand code assembly or
weave compiler ir and i think to a large
extent we we've we've realized that goal
so maybe it's a good point for me
describe one of the core aspects of the
vamp magazine architecture something we
call snippets at the most course level
snippets pure java methods that just
look like in Copiah or like and come up
like any other job method in an idea and
what they are but what they actually
implement parts of JVM bytecode
semantics so we have a snippet for
example called get field and this is a
bit of Java code that has a parameter
which
is an object untyped object and let's
see what else and a constant poll index
which is pretty much what you get from
the JVM if you look at JVM spats
specification the semantics of a get
field is you take a receiver off the
stack which is our object and encoded in
the instruction is a reference to the
constant pool which allows you to
resolve exactly which field of the
object to retrieve so we have this Java
code that simply operates on this object
and is filled and asked the field in
cause method on the field which gets an
offset converts the object to a pointer
which I'll go into more detail involves
many layers of abstraction and at some
point this will boil down to machine
code which dereferences machine address
and returns the value of the field now
this this snippet itself is now a part
of the compiler and that this is where
it gets a bit tricky to understand and
also to explain if you I mean an
immediate observation is well what if
this this bit of Java code itself
references another field don't you have
a sort of infinite recursion problem
here and it's for this reason we have a
two-phase mechanism for bootstrapping
our compiler where all of these snippets
are sort of translated to this this
unoptimized form of an ir which it calls
out or references other pieces of ir and
we need to build this these unoptimized
forms of compiler representation for all
of the snippets and sort of put them on
a table on the side and then recompile
them pulling bits of that table pulling
the the cross-reference semantics out of
this table and running our optimizations
over them and to cut along a confusing
story short what you end up with is
these little bits of bytecode semantics
in a table or
that the compiled and optimized IR for
these bits of semantics indexed in a
table which you then use to compile any
other Java code so every time you see a
gap field you say okay I need I need
this snippet so I go to this table pull
out this IR and weave it into the IR I'm
building for the the method being
compiled so all the compiler really
knows how to do is how to apply standard
optimizations to reduce these snippets
but the actual semantics of what any
bytecode does is expressed in this java
code and this is sort of the core of
what we believe could potentially give
any sort of vm researchers a great deal
of flexibility when you want to modify
the semantics of or experiment with
different ways of implementing certain
by code semantics by byte code
implementations let's see what's a good
example so if we think back to the one
of the motivating examples for this this
whole project how do I support objects
we want to abstract away with the notion
of an object references and so we have
we've encapsulated D sort of
abstractions in something we call
schemes and we have this scheme called
reference scheme and a reference game
has operations like given this reference
give me a bite at this abstract offset
or this this you want you want to read
something out of this reference you want
to dereference this reference to pull
some data out and so what exactly that
entails can be tailored for different
reference scheme implementations and a
clarifying example maybe well maybe
references are just database indexes
every object is really just in a
database
and all an object references is a
database key as opposed to a memory
address and so you could quite easily
implement this this different choice of
how you store objects by only providing
a different concrete implementation of
this reference scheme interface and when
I say in effects you really do mean a
Java interface and so the immediate
observation here is well all of these
layers of abstraction before you know
they provide not only a performance
overhead but surely you're going to get
into the same bootstrapping problems
again trying to use references in
methods which yeah the implementation of
the reference scheme itself will
invariably use references so how do you
how do you reduce this down to two flat
code and the mechanism we have is we
employ a couple of very crucial
annotations when writing these these
scheme implementations and we call them
at fold and inline and by out I just
mean the @ symbol used to write
annotations in Java so we can configure
the VM as we build the VM we provide a
concrete implementation of what we we
yes we bind all of the schemes in the VM
to a concrete choice for each of those
schemes which is hanging off this
globally accessible VM configuration
object and so when you want to do
something through a scheme you
effectively sort of ask the
configuration object give me the
reference scheme object and this is just
a method call but by putting at fold on
that method core the the request for the
VM object we say instead of compiling
this call go and execute it right now
sort of meta evaluation is the common
term for compile time evaluation and so
the compiler now has a concrete object
in its IR through which it can which is
the concrete scheme implementation and
then the methods on that scheme
implementation are either meta evaluated
further or inlined and so we don't have
a you don't actually have calls to calls
to cause to cause they're all in line
through it's almost akin to macro style
in lining this is not heuristic in
lining and at the end of the day for
something like a referee reference of a
reference object reference this all met
evaluates away and compiles down to you
know your standard three or four machine
code instruction sequence for pulling an
object out of memory at an offset from a
given memory address assuming you've you
have your choosing to represent your
objects in a standard memory flat memory
system sounds like the mixing VM is also
nicely extendable by others so by by the
Research Projects or so so if someone
would like to whatever would like to
insert aspect-oriented programming on
the vm level would it be possible to use
the the mixing our hope is that would be
extremely easy and experienced who have
had with collaborators so far seems to
point in that direction recently we had
Alan Gregerson here from the University
of Southern Denmark who has written a
system for doing dynamic updates to Java
applications based on modules and module
system in particular the work he's done
has enabled dynamic updates of NetBeans
modules where you don't have to take the
system down and the type of updates you
can do the ultimate goal is to support
updates
that are as powerful reflect exactly the
type of refactorings you can do to Java
code so at the moment you know the
hotspot VM and other Java VMs can
support dynamic updates without stopping
the VM but it's as far as I believe
constrained to bike method
implementation changes you can't add
methods you can't delete methods can't
add fields you can't change the type
hierarchy also all the sorts of things
you can do with refractory and so he's
working he's used the technique of
bytecode rewriting or instrumentation to
catch transitions across API boundaries
and sort of inserted proxies at those
boundaries such that if you put a new
module into the system all existing
modules in the runtime that binds their
module now go through this proxy object
which will determine where to route
certain method calls or field accesses
and so he's they've gotten a long way
with his work but they were quite
interested in using maxeen to solve some
of the problems they ran into with yeah
a VM agnostic implementation in
particular they cannot instrument a lot
of the core JDK classes without
potentially breaking the VM or I mean I
don't think you can even instrument
these classes at runtime that the
classes in our teach are sort of come
into being before any class loaders
written yeah by extent yeah I developed
or deployed by external developers I get
a chance to instrument them not only
that but there are certain transitions
he can't catch at all and one example
was field accesses from native code
called through j'ni which have handle
onto an object and caught back
through j'ni to dereference that object
to effectively do this you have to go
and change the vm implementation of
what's called the the ji function
interface the way you do up calls from
native code back into the vm that in our
vm is just one class with about well I
think it's 250 methods which is the JVM
ji function interface and it's all
standard Java code so it's it's
absolutely trivial to go and do the
intercept in this implementation we've
also had discussions with mikhail helped
from has a platinum institute in germany
who's interested in doing something like
adding something close to prototype
based support to java so he wants to put
proxy you know and what's made every
object actually two objects so the
delegating object and then one or more
delegate is to which method invocation
Zoar field accesses or other state
accesses go through and this gives you
the ability to do you know rewire the
virtual dispatch of of any method at
runtime much like you get with prototype
based languages and you know our initial
considerations of what you'd need to do
that show that you only have to touch a
few parts of maxine VMT
to get a long way of course until the
experiment is complete we can't be too
sure that we've gotten all the
abstractions correct and and we have a
number of other collaborations with
people sort of building on top of maxine
to do things like software transactional
memory that's a group in some labs in
particular for Ranger and Murata he's
working on that we have a collaboration
with the University of California Irvine
it's Michael Francis group particular
andreas gal Michael Bernina and Karthik
Mahna Mahna van implementing a trace
based compiler in Maxine
this is the same compilation techniques
used in I think it's called trace monkey
one of the optimized JavaScript
optimizing compilers in Firefox or about
to come in Firefox so yeah
current experience shows you know the VM
is penetrable and allows for certain
sorts of experiments to be conducted
fairly easily youyou said that the
maxeen vm it's written in java so it's
it's different than hotspot and can
optimize itself so how does it relate to
the idea that what you already mention
the Jake's research VM so I'd say the
core defining difference is this
architecture we have of building
everything on top of the compiler the
optimizing compiler and expressing sort
of the VM semantics in Java code which
are bootstrapped to become the the
translation units of the compiler if you
look at hotspot the the both compilers
of which I think there are at least two
a sort of hand coded monolithic
implementations where as a maxine
currently we have this this optimizing
compiler around which we build or derive
a JIT compiler so the optimizing pile is
actually relatively slow to execute even
though producers yeah at this point ok
machine code but it's it's unbearably
slow if this was the only execution
engine you had in the VM so what we
built is a very fast template base
JIT compiler and the way to explain this
is if you think about what we do is we
write Java methods that almost look like
you're writing an interpreter in Java
and we compiled these methods and each
method is a one-to-one correspondence
with a JVM bytecode and all it does is
Express the semantics of that bytecode
in Java code we compiled that method
with the optimizing compiler cut out the
resultant machine code and put it in a
table index by that byte codes opcode
and so to run this compiler it's
basically a amend copy operation is the
closest analogy to where we'd like it to
be you passes sequence of byte codes you
pick out the opcode decode the operands
pull this bit of machine code out of the
table if necessary you know patch a few
values in the machine code to represent
the runt the decoded operands and copy
it to a code buffer and the hope is you
know this execution engine is fast
enough that we can do without an
interpreter and in in that sense we're
not too different from jikes which by my
understanding does not have an
interpreter but I think you know the
core difference is this architectural
decision to really build everything
around this optimizing compiler allowing
for the semantics of any part of the VM
to be expressed in one place and there's
other sort of minor artifact differences
you know we came to the game later so we
can we one thing we've tried to stay
away from we've managed so far as any
sort of source code pre-processing
you can download the maxine source code
and it'll come straight up in an ID
without having any sort of quick
configuration applied other differences
at least with jokes from the get-go
we've implemented native threads I here
recently jikes has also implemented
native feds but until until that time
they were empty and sort of green
threaded model where they did their own
scheduling on top of native threads and
if ya there's pros and cons of each but
it seems as though industrial VMS are
going does your strength but
high-performance PM's have always chosen
native threads and that's you know we
learnt from that decision and chose them
from the beginning another interesting
aspect is we have
a single instruction safe point
mechanism safe points in vm's the way in
which you can stop a thread for the
purpose of for example you want to run a
garbage collection you need to be able
to know the execution state and
particularly need to know where all the
references are at the execution state in
the execution set of every thread in the
system safe points are one way to
achieve this way you can make sure each
thread is stopped at a point where you
have some metadata saved describing
where the references are so the safe
point mechanism we have well we needed
one that would allow us to stop not all
threads yeah we don't want a mechanism
where as soon as you trigger as safe
points or thread stop and the main
reason is we have a garbage collector
running on you no written in Java
running on one of our threads so
obviously we can't stop that thread so
we came up with a mechanism where it's
per thread enabled and it actually only
takes one x86 or AMD for 64 instruction
to to to instrument the code to put in
the the polling or is equal point at the
trigger for the safe point we've you
know given that we want to make as many
parts of the VM as can figure as
possible configurable as possible we've
put a lot of work into coming up with
schemes for various parts of the system
we have schemes for how objects are laid
out what references look like a scheme
for what your garbage collector
implementation choice is and numerous
other aspects of a typical VM another we
feel it may be important we're not sure
a difference is that we aim to be and
have so far achieved this goal of being
a drop-in replacement fart spot so you
can download standard JDK
and execute LVM on top of that we don't
were not dependent on canary classpath
or other alternatives to the standard
java class libraries which means we can
always use the latest and greatest and
most complete implementation of the Java
language spec and it obviously means
once our VMs stable and robust we can
run any program hotspot can how was the
performance compare it to hotspot at the
moment at best we're about 2 X slower
than hotspot which you know gets us
close to the threshold for acceptability
in terms of conducting meaningful
performance related experiments although
one could argue you really need to be
even better we have a a good plan for
improving performance which is to
actually leverage a lot of the but one
of the compilers in hotspot effectively
we're porting the client compiler from
hotspot into Maxine with the hope to one
day also using it as our ahead of time
optimizing compiler but there's been a
you know a lot of work a lot of
engineering years thrown at that
compiler and we've decided it's time to
leverage that and also use a compiler
that other people may have more
familiarity with our current optimizing
pal is based on CPS compare continuation
passing style which is what has been
used in sort of implementations of
scheme VMs and scheme compilers but we
found through experience with interns
and other collaborators it's not as well
understood as as a more traditional
compiler which client the client
component hotspot definitely is and it
also allows us to more easily look at
the possibility of transferring some of
this technology back into the product
we've identified some of the areas for
improvement in the client compiler and
we hope to put them in implement them as
we port the compiler ahead hope as we
can back port or Lisa jest these
improvements to the hotspot team
so yeah performance is not quite where
we want it to be but it's definitely
enough to run a vast majority of
programs and conduct interesting
experiments and the hope is those
experiments results will only get more
interesting without having to redo the
experiments as the core compiler
improves so there's no sort of barrier
to conduct an experience on the VM as it
stands right now unless you really need
high performance results immediately we
hope to have this port done within the
next six months and we've also have
ideas the other sub optimal part of the
VM right now is the garbage collector we
have a simple Cheney to space copying
collector non generational so while it's
extremely easy to understand and it's
allowed us to get up and running with a
relatively bug-free collector it's it's
far from optimal and we have a plan one
of the team members Laurent and Eze is
currently working with a hotspot team to
put in a variation of the g1 collector
which is currently in the open JDK
version of hotspot and this is a region
base compiler so you sort of you
petition your memory space up to
different regions and you can sort of
get instead of just generations you can
think of many many generations and you
can get performance benefits by not
having to do as much work if you have
only create garbage in a few regions
so this implementation is currently
being performed by one of our team
members on hotspot code base and the
hope is in the next few months he can
port that also into Maxine and after
that we really went home to many more
excuses for sub hotspot performance
numbers I mean the hope is with both of
those will be at least on par with
hotspot client compiler so yeah that's
that's the performance story today and
hopefully in the short-term future and
what about the hotpot server compiler so
we are not compiler experts I'll say
upfront and that is a compiler not
understood by a lot of people I mean
it's very well designed and highly
optimizing in polar but it's sort of
beyond the scope of our resources to
also try and put that one into Maxine it
would be interesting to have it in there
but we feel doing client is a more
realistic goal and and buys us you know
sufficient performance I mean if you're
in case you know the way up until
recently and I think it may still be the
case at least for the non openjdk
versions of hotspot every time you run
you are either running client or so a
compiler and for a large class of
applications the client compiler is the
default choice or a large set of
platforms the client compiler is the
default choice and so people have been
using only the compiler
client compiler for a long time and
being satisfied with its performance so
it should be good enough for us in the
initially anyway okay I do think that um
the maxeen architecture will will remain
a research project or will be the
production vm of the next generation so
this is where we can get into
controversial statements but I mean my
hope is that it's a bit of both
primarily we hope that it becomes the
primary research platform of choice in
terms of
transfer into product land you know we
have to be honest and safe we're a small
team we don't have the resources to
bring it up to speed or close you know
close enough to the product performance
that quickly and our initial goal is to
just try and chance for some of the
technologies we've developed in the VM
some of the ideas at least into hotspot
so like I mentioned earlier if our
client compiler port actually makes
improvements client compiler we'd like
to at least have the discussion with the
product guys of how to put those
improvements into hotspot a wholesale
replacement of hotspot is a very
futuristic concept at this point okay
yeah I looked at the website and there
are different ports of the machine or
different platforms available that
mixing can run on it's it's all areas
and I think Mac where's yeah so can you
tell us a little bit more which
platforms are available okay so this
point in time there's a sort of
development platform of choice that we
focus on is Solaris amd64
just because that's sort of close to
Sun's core business and it's it's the
hard way we could get our hands on
initially we also have a Solaris spark
port which is lagging a little bit
behind the Solaris MD 64 port just just
because of obviously differences in the
spark back end and we actually have a
new team member Paul Capriati who will
be hopefully addressing that over the
next few months and that's sort of a
particular interest to some of the other
groups looking at using Maxine and Sun
who want to work on especially the
software transactional memory support
which would play nicely on sons of
incoming rock processor or some of sons
highly scalable SPARC processors the
hard part of any port is the back end so
given that we've got amd64 it wasn't too
much
effort to get the VM running on Linux we
so we have a Linux Andy 64 port which
runs as stabilized as far as MD 64 port
we also have the Mac OS port completed
obviously you need to be running yeah a
MacBook or a Mac machine that I think
has the Core 2 Duo processor which is
instruction set compatibles MD 64 and we
found out she'd the hardest part of
these ports apart from the SPARC one was
not so much the VM itself or the
compiled and VM but the debugging
support so we have our own debugger for
this VM and one of the main reasons for
that is it allows us to not be
constrained by the sort of compiled
frame layouts that other debuggers
expect it also allows us to leverage the
fact that we know what objects look like
in the VM so our debugger is both sort
of runtime execution - buggers as well
as a object browser much like you may be
familiar with from a small talk
environment and that the platform
specific part of this this tool has been
remote controlling processes I mean any
debugger has to be at a starter process
or attached to process and control its
execution and inspect its memory the
Solaris OS has wonderful support for
this it's it's we use sort of a C
interface which is really just a C ABI
API alternative to the /proc file system
on Solaris which gives you very liable
ways to stop start single step read
memory from a Solaris process in
particular in what it does very well as
handling Solaris process with multiple
threads that they're very clearly
separated the notion of what Solaris has
a separate notion of process and threads
Darwin was also not too hard there the
problem is your debugging interface is a
mixture of peat race and muck
ABI so there was just a little more
learning to do there but we have the
darwin debugger working almost as well
as any other de bucket there is one one
sort of non understood performance
behavior anomaly that we can't or we
haven't fixed yet and I think the
hardest challenge we had was the Linux
debugger hook up so Linux only presents
you with P trace and P trace closer
reflects the the implementation choice
for threads on Linux which is a thread
is effectively a process and using P
trace you have an interface to a single
process so if that process you know
itself comprises of many threads you
have to do a whole lot of extra
bookkeeping to learn about when those
threads come online when they die and
attach a new P trace interim instance to
each of those threads so that was
basically a couple of weeks of just
staring at and trying to understand the
gdb source code but we've managed to get
the the port completed to the point
where it's actually as easy to debug
maxeen on linux as it is on the solaris
platforms so they are l currently
branded platforms and I'm going to
preempt a question on where is the
Windows port and yes it's just a matter
of lack of resources all of these other
platforms we've ported to a very unique
Slyke and so our thin layer of C code
basically had only minor differences
that needed to be taken care of to make
those ports warwick and you know now
that this is out there as an open source
project we'd love to work with anyone
who'd
like to see this work on windows
obviously in every window is a 64-bit
platform running on AMD 64 but I can't
imagine the the the overhead is too
large so yeah that's a our platform
story at the moment actually let me at
least mention the fact that we say this
VM is written purely in or almost all in
Java implies there is a some native or C
code in there and we've kept that to an
absolute minimum all our C code does for
the most part is implement you know the
main entry point required of C programs
which knows where our boot images and
maps it into memory relocates the the
pointers inside that boot image and then
transfers control into a well-known
method entry point inside the image and
that that's about it in terms of our
seeker the only other thing we do the C
code is we shield some of the sub
platform dependent ways of doing VAR
args from our J&I function
implementations but that there really
isn't much else in the C code in
particular we don't expose any heap
objects to the C code we don't have any
requirement for handles in our C code
and and it's it's it's so far managed to
compile trivially on every C compiler
we've found it out so we don't use any
sort of obscure constructs yeah all I
can say is I encourage people to go to
the maxine website which is at research
sun calm slash project slash maxine and
at least read more documentation what
it's about and if you're interested
download it and build it and play with
it great so doc thank you very much for
being on this
and give us all these interesting
details about the Maxine project so
thank you very much all right thank you
very much Martin and good luck to anyone
who cares to experiment with this
platform would you love to hear back
from you
great thank you thanks Martin thanks for
listening to software engineering radio
software engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team at SC - radio
net or if you're specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of se radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crow and the pot site Music Network for
the music used in this show the song is
called Vegas Achtung
you
[Music]